Guide to the William Henricks Wiser and Charlotte Viall Wiser Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
- Collected Material, 1877-1979; Series VII
  - Addendum 2014
    - Collected materials
      - The Lady of the Lake (book), 1923 (Box 25, Folder 2)
        cloth-bound book, handwritten inscription, "Loch Katrine Aug. 30, 1923, The Wisers".
      - The High Clerc Cookery Book ("Sold by the Principal, High Clerc School for Missionaries' Children, Kodaikanal, Madras Presidency."), 1924 (Box 25, Folder 3)
      - Dance performance programs, 1924, 1940 (Box 25, Folder 4)
      - Telephone directory, United Provinces Circle, with advertisements, services, local contact listings, 1942 (Box 25, Folder 5)
      - Our Educational Emphasis in Primitive Perspective by Margaret Mead (article originally printed in The American Journal of Sociology, Vol. XLVIII, No. 6, May, 1943) (Box 25, Folder 6)
      - Quotation of a statement sent to Dr. Speer on Sept. 25, 1925 by Dr. Sam Higginbottom (recorded by R.K. Sorabji), 1944 (Box 25, Folder 7)
      - Indian and American nutritional education, 1944-1946 (Box 25, Folder 8)
      - Peace Corps Training Program, Biographical Sketches, with handwritten notes by C. Wiser, 1966 (Box 25, Folder 9)
      - Documents regarding religion in India, 1904, 1967, no dates (Box 25, Folder 10)
        news clippings, pamphlets, typed notes, pictures of symbols
      - American Women's Club of Delhi, member directories, 1969-1970, 1971-1972 (Box 25, Folder 11)
      - Some Reflections on Runaways by Margaret K. Rosenheim (Occasional Paper Number 8 August 1977, Univ. of Chicago School of Social Service Administration) (Box 25, Folder 12)
      - Brochures of charitable organizations in India, 1979 (Box 25, Folder 13)
        two brochures with note by C. Wiser, "Institutions I should like to help"
      - Indian newspaper (Sanskrit) (Box 25, Folder 14)
      - Scroll icon of Indian Jesus; scroll showing Indian gods (Box 25, Folder 15)
      - Artwork, incl iconography, socioanthropological, religious; professional and self-taught by friends and others; booklet on Christian Art in India (Box 25, Folder 16)
      - UNESCOPE (book) - poetry and artwork on peace, no date (Box 25, Folder 17)
      - Booklets published by The Educational Resources Center, New Delhi: "Motion Pictures for the Study of India", "A Village of Northern India", "India Through the Ancient Classics", "They Live in India" (Box 25, Folder 18)
      - Artifacts: Blocks for printing "The Wiser Trail - 25th Anniversary", 1936 (Box 31, Folder 1)
      - Artifacts: Blocks for printing illustrations, no date (Box 31, Folder 2)
      - Artifacts: Indian paper money, tikas, embroidered cloth, no date (Box 31, Folder 3)
      - India Village Service note paper, no date (Box 31, Folder 4)
      - Indian language booklet published at Rasalpura Christian High School Press, no date (Box 31, Folder 5)
      - Sketch of Wisers' house in India, no date (Box OVd3)
      - Large colored poster with Indian language and symbols, no date (Box OVd3)
- Biographical Documentation, 1915-1981; Series VIII
  - Addendum 2010
    - Lists of memorable dates, personal records (Box 14, Folder 105)
    - Paper by Susan Snow Wadley: "William and Charlotte Wiser: Missionaries as Scholars and Development Officers", no date (Box 14, Folder 106)
  - Addendum 2014
    - Important dates, 1915-1934; description of activities 1930-1932; certification of William Wiser as father of Alfred Roswell Wiser; Christmas card showing Wiser family (Box 26, Folder 1)
      typed, third-person, author unclear
    - 50 Years in India, Peace Corps Tribute, 1966 (Box 26, Folder 2)
      letters, program
    - The American Women's Club of Delhi Tribute, 1970 (Box 26, Folder 3)
      Certificate of Life Membership, Annual Spring Lunch and Fashion Show programme listing C. Wiser as guest of honor
    - Other tributes - letters and poems, English and Sanskirt, 1941, 1970s, 1981 (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - Behind Mud Walls tour - schedule, news clippings, letter of thanks, 1974 (Box 26, Folder 5)
    - Guestbook, 1966-1975 (Box 26, Folder 6)
    - Documents from United Presbyterian Church USA - death notices, annual reports, directories of retired missionaries, 1972, 1978-1979 (Box 26, Folder 7)
    - Cash ledger, 1930 (Box 26, Folder 8)
    - 4 cash ledgers, 1967-1968, 1970, 1971, 1975 (Box 26, Folder 9)
    - 11 correspondence ledgers, 1968-1981 (Box 26, Folder 10)
    - Documents and notes re travel and activities in retirement, 1968-1972 (Box 26, Folder 11)
      Including re. Egypt, Greece; visa application, passport photo, vacation slides and souvenirs, correspondences regarding travel logistics
    - Wall calendars, 1969, 1978, 1979, 1980, 1981 (Box 26, Folder 12)
- Audio-visual Material, 1913-1970s; Series IX
  - Original collection
    - 2 video tapes of talk by Charlotte Wiser, Syracuse University, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 51)
    - Two photograph albums about India Village Service, with accompanying scripts (Box 7, Folder 52-53)
  - Addendum 2014
    - Photographs
      - Indian individuals: portraits and shown at work with various crafts and other activities, 1916-1930s, no date (Box 27, Folder 1)
      - Indian individuals: portraits and scenes of daily life, 1920s-1930s, no date (Box 27, Folder 2)
      - Indian individuals: portraits and scenes of daily life, 1920s-1930s, no date (Box 27, Folder 3)
      - Indian individuals: portraits and scenes of daily life, 1920s-1930s, no date (Box 27, Folder 4)
      - Indian individuals: portraits and scenes of daily life, 1920s-1930s, no date (Box 27, Folder 5)
      - Indian groups: portraits and scenes of daily life, 1920s-1930s, no date (Box 27, Folder 6)
      - Indian groups: portraits and scenes of daily life, 1920s-1930s, no date (Box 27, Folder 7)
      - Indian groups: portraits and scenes of daily life, 1920s-1949, no date (Box 27, Folder 8)
      - Indian groups: portraits and scenes of daily life, 1920s-1970, no date (Box 27, Folder 9)
      - Indian groups: portraits and scenes of daily life, interactions with missionaries, 1916-1930s, no date (Box 27, Folder 10)
      - Indian groups: including school groups and family portraits, 1920s-1930s, no date (Box 27, Folder 11)
      - Indian groups: villagers, family portraits, 1920s-1930s no date (Box 27, Folder 12)
      - Indian groups: scenes of village life, school classes, interaction with missionaries, 1916-1930s, no date (Box 27, Folder 13)
      - Indian groups: scenes of village life, 1920s-1930s, no date (Box 27, Folder 14)
      - Portraits of miscellaneous Western adults and children, 1916-1960s, no date (Box 28, Folder 1)
      - Portraits of miscellaneous Western adults and children, 1920s-1970s (Box 28, Folder 2)
      - Western groups: including scenes in India, 1920s-1940s (Box 28, Folder 3)
      - Western groups: including families, missionaries, 1917-1940s, no date (Box 28, Folder 4)
      - Western groups: families, 1920s-1960s, no date (Box 28, Folder 5)
      - Western groups: families, missionaries, 1912-1940s, no date (Box 28, Folder 6)
      - Western groups: including children at Annual Meeting of North India Mission, Landour, 1928, no date (Box 28, Folder 7)
      - Portraits of Charlotte Wiser, 1940s-1970s (Box 28, Folder 8)
      - Portraits of William Wiser, 1913-1951 (Box 28, Folder 9)
      - Portraits of Charlotte and William Wiser, 1933, 1950s (Box 28, Folder 10)
      - Charlotte Wiser with various individuals, including in India, 1960s-1970s, no date (Box 28, Folder 11)
      - Wisers' home in Lucknow, 1948-1951 (Box 29, Folder 1)
      - Buildings and scenes in India, with identification, 1915-1919 (Box 29, Folder 2)
      - Buildings and scenes in India, with identification, 1920s (Box 29, Folder 3)
      - Buildings and scenes in India, with identification, 1943-1950, 1971 (Box 29, Folder 4)
      - Buildings and scenes, primarily in India, no date (Box 29, Folder 5)
      - Buildings and scenes in India, no date (Box 29, Folder 6)
      - Buildings and scenes, primarily in India, no date (Box 29, Folder 7)
      - Buildings and scenes, primarily in India, no date (Box 29, Folder 8)
      - Buildings and scenes in India, no date (Box 29, Folder 9)
      - Sequence of photos showing hands of Indian woman and some custom or ritual, no date (Box 29, Folder 10)
      - Postcards, primarily depicting India, no date (Box 29, Folder 11)
      - Photos removed from album, primarily of children in India, 1920s? (Box 29, Folder 12)
      - Photos removed from album, primarily of women in India, no date (Box 29, Folder 13)
      - Photos removed from album, primarily individuals and scenes in India, 1920s-1930s (Box 29, Folder 14)
      - Proof sheets of photographs suggested for Charlotte Wiser's book, Four Families, no date (Box 29, Folder 15)
      - Three albums of negatives including some prints, including photographs of children in India, agriculture, no date (Box 29, Folder 16)
      - One album of negatives, several envelopes of negatives, some identified, no date (Box 29, Folder 17)
      - Envelopes of negatives, some identified, no date (Box 30, Folder 1)
    - Slides
      - Glass lantern slides (19 boxes), 1916-1920s? (Box OV1)
        Forty slides from first five boxes scanned and available on CD.
      - 35 mm slides: several boxes and packets, some identified, including slides for presentation on India Village Services, no date (Box 30, Folder 2)
    - Filmstrip
      - Two copies of filmstrip titled "Looking Behind Mud Walls" (Box 30, Folder 3)